Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco.
My name is Catherine
and today we have an
elementary level lesson
in which we're going to talk
about small talk. That's right, today we're
going to talk to an old friend and so we're
going to give you some of
the words and phrases you need
to talk about your past or
talk about how you have been.
So let's listen to today's
dialogue and we'll be back
in a moment to discuss
it. I hate coming to a
high school reunions.
It'll be great, honey.
We will get to see your old classmates
and catch up to see how they've been doing.
Ah yeah I guess so. Oh look, there's Robert
Matthews. Rob. Hey Bill, wow, great to
see you. Likewise, it's been a long time.
This is my wife Dorothy.
Pleasure to meet you. So Bill, how have you
been? Can't complain. We have two children
who are in college and my business is
going well. How about you? Ah, you know me.
I'm a dedicated bachelor.
I never married although
I do have a beautiful
daughter with Mary.
You remember her? We
were high school sweethearts.
It didn't really work
out between us
but I really can't complain either.
That's good. Have you seen Frank?
I was hoping he would
come tonight. You didn't hear?
Frank passed away last
year. Are you serious?
Nah, I'm just janking your chain. He'll
be here soon. I saw him last week. He told
me he would show up. All right, we're back.
So now let's get started with our language
takeaway. Language takeaway.
The first phrase we have here in language
takeaway is a very important one because
it is the setting for today's dialogue.
We are at a high school
reunion. That's right.
So everyone knows what
high school is. But a high
school reunion is when you go back to your
high school. For a party, maybe five years
or 10 years after you graduate. So then you
meet all your old friends from high school.
You talk about, you know, how you have been
and just meet up with everyone that maybe
you haven't seen in a
very long time. Exactly.
So a reunion usually
happens every five
years, 10 years or 20
years. It can happen at
different times. But
this is important because
you can have many
different kinds of reunions
like a college reunion
or high school reunion.
I've even heard of some people who had
an elementary school reunion. Really? Wow.
Imagine seeing your classmates when you
were maybe 10 years old. I couldn't imagine.
All right. So we're at
a high school reunion
and we are there because
we're going to meet
our old classmates
and to catch up and see
how they have been.
Okay. So this is exactly
what you do at a
reunion. You catch up with
people that you maybe
lost touch with to catch
up means to find out about what people have
been doing since the last time you talked.
So maybe Marco and I
were classmates in high
school and we haven't
talked in 10 years.
As a Marco, I want to catch up.
I want to learn about what
you do, who you've married,
where you work, things like that. Right. So
when two people get together to catch up,
maybe it doesn't even
have to be a very long time.
Maybe you haven't seen
your friend for a week.
And so you want to get together,
have a cup of coffee and catch up and see
how the relationship has
been going or how it works.
So you want to catch up.
So you can say this in a
very simple way. Let's catch up
or it's been nice to
catch up. That's right.
All right. Moving on to our next word. This
guy Bill meets up with Robert Matthews and
they're saying, Hey, wow, great to see you.
And he answers by saying likewise. So it's
good to see you likewise. Right. That means
it's good to see you too. So you don't have
to repeat everything that person just said.
For example, if I just meet someone new and
I say, it's a pleasure to meet you, you
can say, I could say likewise likewise.
Because I don't want to say,
it's a pleasure to meet you too.
That's so many words.
So likewise is a very short
way to say all of those things.
That's right. So we were finding out about
Robert Matthews. And he says that, well,
he is a dedicated bachelor. So a dedicated
bachelor, what is a bachelor, Marco?
So a bachelor is a person
who is not married, a person
who is single, a man, a
woman cannot be a bachelor.
So a bachelor is
specifically a man.
And he's not married. And
we often have a stereotype.
That means we have an idea of what a
bachelor lives like, you know, he has only
beer in his refrigerator,
and he has many
relationships and no
wife. So that's right.
So a dedicated bachelor
is a person who is not
married and doesn't really seem to want
to get married or any of this. He wants to
space single. Exactly. Okay.
And well, to finish off, this
guy Robert lied a little bit
to Bill saying that Frank had passed away.
That's really mean. But this phrase to pass
away is very important and
something we should talk about.
So what does it
mean to pass away?
It's another way
of saying he died.
So but it's nicer. Yeah, it's
a lot more subtle and nicer.
So instead of saying, Frank
died, you say, Frank passed away.
So you could say, you know,
last year, my grandmother passed
away as a way of saying that
my grandmother died last year.
But again, it's a lot nicer way to
say right because the word died can
be a little bit too direct and too harsh.
So maybe saying my grandmother passed away
last year. It's a nicer way of saying it.
Okay. So that's all the language tickle you
you have. Let's take a look at our
dialogue again and we'll be back.
Hi. Hey, coming to
high school reunions.
It'll be great, honey.
We will get to see your
old classmates and catch up
to see how they've been doing.
Yeah, I guess so.
Oh, look, there's Robert
Matthews. Rob. Hey, Bill.
Wow. Great to see you. Likewise.
It's been a long time.
This is my wife Dorothy.
Pleasure to meet you. So
Bill, how have you been?
Can't complain. We
have two children who are
in college and my
business is going well.
How about you? Ah, you know
me. I'm a dedicated bachelor.
I never married, although I do
have a beautiful daughter with Mary.
You remember her. We
were high school sweethearts.
It didn't really work out
between us, but I really can't
complain either. That's
good. Have you seen Frank?
I was hoping he
would come to note.
You didn't hear Frank
passed away last year.
Are you serious? Nah,
I'm just janking your chain.
It'll be your soon. I
saw him last week.
He told me he would
show up. All right.
Let's move on now to four
key phrases on fluency builder.
Fluency builder. So the focus of
today's fluency builder is small talk.
These are phrases you
can use when you're at a
reunion or dinner,
especially with people you
don't know very well.
So let's jump in and
look at this first
phrase. Great to see you.
That's right. So
he says, "Hey, Bill.
Wow, great to see you."
So this is a nice little opening
phrase saying, "Wow, I'm
really excited to see you.
I'm really happy
to see you." Exactly.
It means I'm happy. Look at you.
You know, great to
see you. You say this at
the beginning of a
conversation. That's right.
And actually Bill responded
by saying likewise.
So we talked about this. He's
saying, "Wow, great to see you too.
" Then he continues by saying, "It's been
a long time." This means that these two
people, they have not seen
each other in a very long time.
You can also say,
"It's been so long.
" Or, "It's been a long time.
" That means it's been a long
time since we last saw each other.
That's right. So Robert
goes on to ask Bill.
He says, "Well, you
know, how have you been?
How are things?" Bill answers
by saying, "Can't complain." Okay. So this
is not grammatically correct. Normally, you
need a subject. I can't complain. But when
we're speaking in English and we're having
a conversation like this, it's okay to
say, "Just can't complain as a phrase.
" So he's saying, "Have you
been? Well, I can't complain.
" Or, "Can't complain."
That means nothing
bad has happened. Things are okay.
Right. You're saying that things are good.
They're not fantastic, but they're not
bad either. So you can't really complain.
So it's just a phrase where
very directly you can say,
"Oh, can't complain.
Everything's great.
" So you could even say
this about other things.
Like, you know, I asked
John how his job was
and he said, "No,
can't complain." Right.
It means not great,
but it's not bad. Right.
Exactly, right. All
right. And obviously, we
saw how Robert lied
to Bill by saying that
they're a good friend,
that they're a good friend.
Frank had passed away
and he said, "Are you serious?
Nah. I'm just
yanking your chain.
" Okay. So this might
sound very strange
to a lot of you because
a chain is something
that doesn't really seem
to fit in this conversation.
Right. But yanking your chain, remember this
as a phrase. It means, "I'm just joking.
" Right. I'm not
serious. Hitting.
I'm lying to you, I
guess, right? So, but how
can you use this in another context? Okay.
I could say, you know what, Marco, I have
something I have to
tell you. And I say what?
I'm leaving English pot.
I quit. Are you serious?
No. I'm just yanking your chain. Okay. Or
no, I'm just kidding. Right. So you're kind
of teasing someone when you do this, right?
I'm just yanking your chain. I'm just lying
to you. I'm teasing
you. I'm making you
believe something
that isn't that isn't true.
Exactly. So this is
something you can use after
you tell someone that
you were just joking.
So, you know, I'm just yanking your chain.
I'm just joking with you.
That's right. So
don't try to translate it
directly or literally because
it's not going to make sense.
So just remember this as a phrasal
verb or a phrase in general. Exactly.
All right. Let's listen
to our dialogue one
last time and we'll be
back to talk a little bit more.
I hate coming to a
high school reunions.
It'll be great, honey.
We will get to see your
old classmates and catch up
to see how they've been doing.
Ah, yeah, I guess so. Oh, look.
There's Robert Matthews.
Rob. Hey, Bill. Wow.
Great to see you. Likewise, it's been
a long time. This is my wife Dorothy.
Pleasure to meet you. So,
Bill, how have you been?
Can't complain. We
have two children
who are in college and my business
is going well. How about you?
Ah, you know me. I'm
a dedicated bachelor.
I never married, although
I do have a beautiful
daughter with Mary.
You remember her.
We were a high school
sweetheart. It didn't really
work out between us, but I
really can't complain either.
That's good. Have
you seen Frank?
I was hoping he would
come tonight. You didn't hear?
Frank passed away last
year. Are you serious?
Nah, I'm just janking your
chain. He'll be here soon.
I saw him last week. He
told me he would show up.
All right, so we're
back and talking about
high school reunions.
These are very popular
in the United States, right? They are very
popular and I think people often have them
every five, 10, 15, 20
years, but most people
don't go to the high
school reunion until
either 10 or 20 years after
their high school graduate.
Why then? I think at
five years is very soon.
Ten years is nice because you haven't
seen people, but 20 years is really
I think shocking
because people can be
completely different or
they could be the same.
But it's been, you know,
you were 18 when you
graduated high school.
Now you're 38 years old.
You have this whole
life that you've had.
And so I think it's
much more interesting.
Yeah, it's, it's
very interesting.
And I guess people go to
these things half because they
do want to maybe
meet up with old friends
that they haven't kept
in touch with. I think
especially this was very popular before the
whole internet revolution. Now everyone's
in touch on Facebook and emails and
it's just so much easier to keep in touch.
But before you have to
remember that, you know, it was
basically by telephone
or by mail. So actually
seeing a person 10 years or catching
up with them was very difficult back then.
Yeah, we, we all see photos
and videos now of our classmates.
So it's not quite as surprising when
we go into them later. But I think it
is still interesting
though, because at least
on my social networking
websites, there are
a lot of people that I
don't have connections
to. And so I look forward to my high school
reunion when I get to see some of these
people and find out what they've been doing
for the past 10 or 15 years. It's actually
very interesting, I guess, when you see how
your classmates have changed, how maybe the
one that used to be the
nerd or maybe not to,
not very attractive,
all of a sudden is really
attractive and has like a supermodel
as a wife or how these things work out.
Or the high school football
captain is now kind of sad and so fat.
So yeah, these are
the types of surprises
that people look forward to when they go to
high school reunions. So a very interesting
subject. Let us know on
our website, Englishpot.
com. If you're high
school in the place
where you live, do they
have high school reunions
or maybe even
elementary school reunions?
Yeah, let us know. We
hope to find out more
about you guys's experiences.
And until next time, bye.